Guide to the Tomie Arai and Legan Wong Papers MSS.439
Fales Library and Special Collections
Tomie Arai and Legan Wong Papers
1937-2010
1970-1999
Fales Library and Special Collections
Arai, Tomie, 1949-
Wong, Legan
MSS.439
35 Linear Feet in 39 manuscript boxes, 1 tall manuscript box, 1 record carton, 1 flat box, 6 oversize flat boxes, and 4 flat-file folders
5 Sound_Disc--Vinyl
1 Sound_Disc--Lacquer
1 VHS
Artist and community activist Tomie Arai (1949- ) has been working as an artist in the New York City area since the 1960s, and together with Legan Wong (1951- ) has also been involved with the New York-based Asian American cultural movement since the 1970s. The Tomie Arai and Legan Wong Papers document arts and cultural organizations in New York specifically focused on the Asian American experience including Cityarts Workshop, Basement Workshop, and Godzilla Asian American Art Network. Some of the publications and posters in the collection are bilingual in English and either Japanese, Korean, or Chinese. This collection also contains exhibition catalogues and ephemera accumulated by Arai and Wong which primarily focused on New York-based Asian American artists active during the 1970s to the early 2000s. Arai's work as an artist is documented in this collection through exhibition promotional material, original drawings, printwork created for publications and community organizations, correspondence and project files. This collection also includes materials created and collected by Legan Wong documenting his creation of college courses on the Asian American experience in the 1970s as well as a small amount of material related to his music production work with East West World Records in the 1980s. This collection also contains material related to Wong's participation in the Asian Tactical Theater, Soh Daiko, and an Asian American Softball League team in New York. Materials from Arai's early life and family include Arai's elementary and high school memorabilia from the 1960s and items accumulated by Arai's parents specifically related to their experience as people of Japanese descent in the United States during and after World War II. These materials include research, publications produced and distributed at individual facilities, and original artwork by Arai's uncle, Unosuke Sasaki, created during his period of incarceration at the Topaz Relocation Center, a concentration camp in Utah, in the early 1940s.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Tomie Arai, 2015. The accession number associated with this gift is 2015.439.
Appraisal
Three record cartons of duplicate print material, including exhibition announcements and catalogues and newsclippings, were identified and removed from the collection. The commercially produced record album: Chairman Mao's 4 Minute Physical Fitness Program (1973) was separated from the collection. Approximately 50 collectible buttons were sorted and only those specifically pertaining to the Asian American movement and community were retained. Two mounted items including an illustration: "Unidad de todas" and a reproduction of a photograph of a group with fists in air were removed from the collection. Arai's resource/reference book titles were reviewed and removed if they already existed within the NYU Library's holdings. A list of those removed is available.
Three commercially available record albums owned by Arai's parents (1937 Billie Holiday song, Pat Suzuki Broadway album, and Broadway musical soundtrack, Flower Drum Song album) have been retained in the collection because they were part of Arai's parents' personal collection, two are autographed, and the Broadway show had Asian American performers.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in four series, which have been arranged in chronological order within each series. Files with the same title are grouped together and arranged chronologically within that group.
The series arrangement of the papers is as follows:
Series I. Community Activism
Series II. Tomie Arai Artwork
Series III. Legan Wong Work Files
Series IV. Tomie Arai Early Life and Family
Biographical Note
Tomie Arai (1949- ) was born in New York City and is a third generation Japanese American. She has been creating and exhibiting her artwork since the 1960s. In the 1970s she worked at the Basement Workshop on various projects and the Cityarts Workshop, where she worked as a resource center coordinator and mural director. Arai then worked as a freelance graphic artist for Alan Okada of Citibank, creating posters, brochures and promotional materials for community groups as part of Citibank's Graphic Support program. Arai has been involved in many community-based art projects, creating site-specific public works of art commissioned by the New York City Department of Cultural Affairs' Percent for Art Program, the General Services Administration of the Federal Government, and the NYC MTA Arts for Transit Program.
As an Asian American activist she has participated in the political movements since the 1960s and continues her involvement through organizations including the Museum of Chinese in the Americas. She also served as NYU Asian/Pacific/American Institute's first Artist-in-Residence in 1997-1998 and in 2005.
Biographical Note
Legan Wong (1951- ) was born in Brooklyn, New York, to Chinese immigrant parents. Wong was active in the New York Asian American Movement during the 1970s and 1980s. From 1971 to 1973, he served as a coordinator for the Basement Workshop and was also active in the Asian American Resource Center.
While Wong was an undergraduate at Queens College and later as an adjunct lecturer at Hunter College, he worked to promote the development and expansion of Asian American Studies. Wong was eventually hired at Hunter College to teach a course called The Asian American Experience, a historical and contemporary examination of the experiences of Asians in America. Wong was a member of Asians in the Spirit of the Indo-Chinese (ASI) and Asian Americans for Equal Employment (AAFEE), which focused on workers' rights, racism, and police brutality. Wong also worked as a researcher and freelance writer for the Council on Interracial Books for Children. Between 1982 and 1985, Wong worked as one of the executive producers of East West World Records. The record company produced the album Back to Back and Visions and Dreams.
Wong was involved in a number of local community groups, including the Asian Tactical Theatre, a collective of Asian American activists involved in helping to develop the Asian American cultural front of the larger Asian American Movement. Wong was also a member of Soh Daiko, a taiko drum performance group based at the New York Buddhist Church, and a member of a team in the Asian American Softball League in New York.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual material that has not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Material not yet digitized will need to have an access copy made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Scope and Contents
The Tomie Arai and Legan Wong Papers document the spouses' work in the arts, Asian American Studies, and the Asian American Movement in New York dating from the 1970s to the early 2000s. Older materials in this collection relate to Arai as a student in New York and documentation accumulated by Arai's parents and other family members regarding the incarceration of Japanese Americans during World War II. The collection includes exhibition ephemera, Asian American community publications, drawings and prints, correspondence, photographs, and bilingual event posters and announcements in English and either Chinese, Japanese or Korean.
This collection contains material on Arai and Wong's involvement in large and smaller Asian American activist-driven organizations including the Basement Workshop, Cityarts Workshop, and Godzilla Asian American Art Network which have historically been under-documented in larger arts and cultural institutions. These organizations files typically contain promotional material, newsclippings, correspondence, and event posters with printwork by Arai. This collection also contains a large amount of material accumulated by Arai and Wong on Asian American artists' exhibitions and performances in the New York City area during the 1970s through 2000s, including posters, fliers, artist prints, and informational brochures.
A large portion of the collection documents Arai's work from the 1970s to the 2000s, including exhibition announcements and catalogues, correspondence, press materials, and work files for the exhibitions Mi Familia Mi Comunidad, and Chinese y Criollo, a collaborative oral history and art project. This collection also contains publications, posters, drawings, prints, and proofs from Arai's work as a graphic artist for Citibank, focusing primarily on promotional material for small New York Asian American community groups.
Legan Wong's files document his development of university classes on the Asian American experience, including source material, lecture plans, correspondence, and conference notes and information. His files also contain information on community groups he was involved with, including the Asian Americans for Equal Employment (AAFEE), Asian in the Spirit of the Indochinese (ASI), and the Asian Tactical Theater. Correspondence and informational material on the American Softball League in New York and the Soh Daiko performance group illustrate his involvement in the Asian American cultural community as well.
A small amount of older material in this collection relates to Arai's junior high school and early adult years in the 1960s and also contains ephemera and print material accumulated by her parents during the 1940s and 1950s, some of which concerns the incarceration of Japanese Americans during World War II. Materials include research, publications produced and distributed at individual facilities, and original artwork by Arai's uncle, Unosuke Sasaki, created during his period of incarceration at the Topaz Relocation Center, a concentration camp in Utah, in the early 1940s.
Asian American art.; Asian American artists.; Public art -- New York (N.Y.); Public art -- United States.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States.; Watercolors (paintings); Illustrations (layout features).; Asian Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Asian American artists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Exhibitions.; Artists and community -- New York (N.Y); Asian American artists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies.; World War, 1939-1945.; War Relocation Authority (United States); Japanese American artists.; Japanese Americans |x Civil rights |x History |y 20th century.; Japanese American removal, 1942-1945; Arai, Tomie, 1949-; Basement Workshop; Lower East Side Printshop, Inc.; New York University. Asian/Pacific/American Studies Program and Institute; Museum of Chinese in the Americas; African Burial Ground (New York, N.Y.); Godzilla Asian American Art Network
- Series I. Community Activism, 1966-2009; 15 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes, 1 tall legal manuscript box, 1 record carton, 1 flat box, 3 oversize flat boxes, and 4 flat-file folders.; 1 Sound_Disc--Vinyl; 1 VHS
  Scope and Contents
  This series primarily consists of materials related to Arai and Wong's involvement in the Asian American Movement, particularly their engagement with grassroots and arts-related organizations and institutions. Many of these organizations were small Asian American artist-driven organizations within New York, representing the needs and interests of this community during the 1970s and 1980s.
  This series includes files on the Cityarts Workshop, a nonprofit community mural arts organization in the 1970s that created murals by and for communities of color. Arai's artwork was used heavily for the organization's publications and posters during her time with them. Files include promotional material, press clippings, correspondence, presentations, mural planning notes, newsletters, original sketches by artists, and photographs of events, artwork, and artists working on murals. This series also includes publications and leaflets used as inspiration for graphics and murals.
  In the 1970s, Arai and Wong both worked for the Basement Workshop, which was one of the first Asian-American political, community, and arts organizations in New York City. This series contains files on projects produced by this organization, including proofs for the record album A Grain of Sand: Music for the Struggle by Asians in America and production files for the publication Yellow Pearl. Organizational records also contain photographs, promotional material, event announcements, and member lists. Many of the printed items contain Arai's artwork.
  This series also contains meeting notes, letterhead, event announcements, member lists, correspondence, historic timelines, and newsletters for the Godzilla Asian American Arts Network, a New York-based Asian American arts collective and support network in the 1990s, of which Arai was a founding member. Planning files on the exhibition A New World Order are in this series, as well as a Godzilla award figurine, two graphic hats, a t-shirt, newsletters, and a video recording containing interviews with Godzilla members.
  Other New York organizations with files in this series are the Museum of Chinese in the Americas (previously the New York Chinatown History Project), New York Asian Women's Center, United Asian Communities Center, Asian American Arts Alliance, and Chinatown Health Clinic. These files typically include event invitations and programs, informational brochures and booklets, posters, and correspondence. There is also a small collection of buttons in this series, documenting various Asian political causes and arts groups.
  - Asian American Resource Material, 1966-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1-9, Box 2, Folder 1-10, Box 42, Folder 1, Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Asian American Community Event Posters, 1970, 1985, undated (Box 47, Folder 12, Flat-file-folder 2, Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Gidra: Monthly of the Asian American Community, 1971-1874, 1990 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Cityarts Workshop, 1972-2006 (Box 2, Folder 11-12, Box 3, Folder 1-8, Box 4, Folder 1-15, Box 41, Folder 1, Box 43)
  - Basement Workshop, 1972-1988 (Box 5, Folder 16-17, Box 6, Folder 1, Box 41, Folder 2, Box 43, Folder 3, Box 47, Folder 14, Flat-file-folder 1, Flat-file-folder 4)
  - Basement Workshop -- A Grain of Sand: Music for the Struggle by Asians in America Phonodisc, and Concert Poster Printed and Designed by Legan Wong, 1973, 1997 (Box 48, Folder 4, Flat-file-folder 2)
  - Basement Workshop -- Yellow Pearl Production Files, 1972-1997, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 2, Box 47, Folder 5, Flat-file-folder 3)
  - United Asian Community Center, 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Asian American Studies Conferences, 1973, 1980, 1997-2003 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - Asian American Groups, 1977-1994 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Event Posters Illustrated by Mary Hom, 1979-1982 (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Women's Groups Promotional Material, 1979-1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Japanese Americans -- Exhibitions, Museum, and Los Angeles Cultural Organizations, 1981-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1-3, Flat-file-folder 2)
  - New York Asian Women's Center, 1983-1997, undated (Box 7, Folder 4-5, Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Museum of Chinese in the Americas (MOCA) / New York Chinatown History Project -- Exhibitions, Board Material, Promotional Ephemera, 1983-2005 (Box 7, Folder 6, Box 8, Folder 1-7, Box 9, Folder 1, Box 43, Folder 7, Box 47, Folder 9)
  - New Asian Times and Asian New Yorker, 1988-1989, 1993-1995 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Asian American Arts Alliance, 1991-2003 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Godzilla Asian American Art Network -- Member Lists, Event and Exhibition Announcements, Clippings, 1991-2002 (Box 9, Folder 3-9)
  - Godzilla Asian American Art Network -- Timeline, Newsletters, 1991-1994, 2004 (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Godzilla Asian American Art Network -- T-Shirt and Hats, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 40)
  - Godzilla Asian American Art Network--Godzilla with Glitter Award, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 49)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    This item is fragile and glitter can easily become detached from Godzilla's body. This item must be handled with care.
  - Godzilla Asian American Art Network -- From Basement to Godzilla: Asian American Activism in the Arts, 1998
    - Limited Edition Portfolio (Box 40)
    - Video, cuid41029 (Box 48, Vhs 439.0001)
      Duration: 120 minutes
  - Asian American Arts Centre, 2009, undated (Box 9, Folder 10, Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Assorted Buttons (12) -- For Political Causes, Community Organizations, and Cultural Institutions, undated (Box 41)
  - Chinatown Health Clinic Benefit -- Event Poster, undated (Box 47, Folder 13)
- Series II. Tomie Arai Artwork, 1970-2010; 20 Linear Feet in 25 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, 4 oversize flat boxes, and 3 flat-file folders.
  This series contains materials created and accumulated by Arai on the research, production, and exhibition of her artwork, as well as her involvement in the Asian American arts community in New York. The overlap in her artwork and activism is often apparent in the art theme, her projects, and where the works are shown.
  Arai's large collection of exhibition catalogues and ephemera by Asian artists in this series spans the 1970s to the 2000s and not only shows artists active during this timeframe but also the themes that were popular during various decades, as well as which New York galleries and museums were representing and showing their work.
  This series also contains a comprehensive collection of Arai's own exhibition catalogues, announcements, fliers, and related correspondence dating from 1970 to 2000s which shows the volume of projects she was involved with from year to year. The correspondence especially illustrates the work involved to promote herself and her art, apply for funding, plan exhibitions, loan out artworks, and network with galleries and institutions. Projects of note include Double Happiness and Mi Familia Mi Comunidad and Renewal, which was commissioned for the African Burial Ground National Monument.
  Work files, publications, and posters related to Arai's printmaking and illustration work date from the 1970s to the 1990s, mostly for local New York organizations including Cityarts, Basement Workshop, and Chinatown Health Clinic. These posters are often multi-lingual, depending on the organization. Publications containing Arai's work include Heresies, Upfront, and East Village Review. Arai also illustrated a children's book China's Bravest Girl, and this series contains correspondence, reviews, promotional material as well as the book.
  Throughout her career, Arai was the recipient of many residencies and fellowships to fund the progress of her art and related projects. This series includes files for Goddard-Riverside Community Center, New York Foundation for the Arts (NYFA), MoMA PS 1, MacDowell Colony, and Cummington Artist Colony and usually contain correspondence, applications, project reports, and event announcements. Material related to her 1998 Artist in Residency with the New York University Asian/Pacific/American Institute are also in this series.
  - Film, Performances, and Theater by Asian Americans -- Event and Promotional Ephemera, 1970-2008 (Box 9, Folder 11, Box 10, Folder 1, Flat-file-folder 2)
  - Exhibitions by Asian Artists -- Catalogues and Ephemera, 1970s (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Exhibitions by Asian Artists -- Catalogues and Ephemera, 1980s (Box 10, Folder 3-5, Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Exhibitions by Asian Artists -- Catalogues and Ephemera, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 1-4, Box 12, Box 13, Folder 1-5, Box 14, Folder 1-3, Box 42, Folder 2, Box 47)
  - Exhibitions by Asian Artists -- Catalogues and Ephemera, 2000s (Box 14, Folder 4-5, Box 15, Folder 1-4, Box 16, Box 17, Folder 1, Box 41, Folder 3, Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Exhibitions by Asian Artists -- Catalogues and Ephemera, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Calendar Posters -- One is Me..., and Year of the Pig 1983, 1972, 1983 (Box 47, Folder 7, Flat-file-folder 3)
  - Drawings and Illustrations for Movement Leaflets, circa 1972-1979 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Drawings and Illustrations for Community Groups, 1972-1985 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Drawings, Proofs, and Prints for Events, Organizations, and Publications, 1972-2004, undated (Box 19, Folder 8-11, Box 41, Folder 4, 7-9, Box 43, Folder 8-13, Box 47, Folder 8, Flat-file-folder 1)
  - Drawings and Illustrations for Asian Women's Groups, 1974-1982 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Drawings for Publications -- Bridge, East Wind, and Others, 1975-1989 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Arai Exhibitions -- Catalogues and Ephemera, 1976-1978 (Box 17, Folder 7, Box 43, Folder 18)
  - Arai Exhibitions -- Catalogues and Ephemera, 1980s (Box 18, Folder 1-3, Box 43, Folder 18, Box 47, Folder 4, Flat-file-folder 2)
  - Arai Exhibitions -- Catalogues and Ephemera, 1990s (Box 18, Folder 4-5, Box 19, Folder 1-5, Box 43, Folder 19)
  - Arai Exhibitions -- Catalogues and Ephemera, 2006 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Chinatown Health Clinic Event Posters, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 47, Folder 6, Flat-file-folder 3)
  - Illustrations -- Interracial Books for Children, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Illustrations -- Winning Justice for All Student and Teacher Workbooks, circa 1977-1978 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Illustrations -- Ethnic Woman Magazine, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Illustrations -- Heresies, 1980-1990 (Box 20, Folder 3-4, Box 41, Folder 5, Box 43, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence -- Re: Exhibitions, Donations, Artwork, 1980-1995, 2001-2002, undated (Box 20, Folder 5, Box 21, Folder 1-5, Box 22, Folder 1-6, Box 23, Folder 1, Box 33)
  - Memory in Progress: Mother/Daughter Project -- Exhibition Files, Promotional Material, Clipping, 1982-1989 (Box 23, Folder 2-3, Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Lucy Lippard, Heresies, and PADD (Political Art Documentation/Distribution) Projects, 1982-1998 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - PADD (Political Art Documentation/Distribution) Publication -- Upfront, 1983-1986 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Printmaking Workshop, 1985-1995, 2003 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Printshops -- Information, 1985-2010 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Goddard-Riverside Community Center -- Exhibitions and Programs, 1986-1992 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Coast to Coast: National Women Artists of Color -- Exhibitions, Promotional Material, Newsletters, Posters, 1986-1997 (Box 24, Folder 3-4, Box 43, Folder 15)
  - Printshops -- Women's Studio Workshop and Avocet, 1986-2005 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Printshop -- Lower East Side Printshop, 1986-2005 (Box 25, Folder 1-3, Box 43, Folder 5, Box 47, Folder 10)
  - Ikon Magazine -- Illustrations and Projects, 1987-1990 (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
  - Press Clippings, 1987-1998 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Cummington Community and School of the Arts -- Participant Material, 1989 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Memories of New York Chinatown -- Banner Installation and Exhibition, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 1, Box 44, Folder 3)
  - PS 1 -- National Studio Program, 1990-1991 (Box 26, Folder 2, Box 43, Folder 17)